<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../Template/schema/VHLTEINew.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <?TEIVERSION 1.3.0. Last updated on February 1st 2009.?>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Oratio</title>
                <author>Pico</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Revised and edited by</resp>
                    <name>Andrew Ashton</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>Dongbo Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Scholarly Technology Group, Brown University</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Box 1841, Brown University, Providence, RI 02912</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="1968">2008</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc n="[NUMBER FROM THE SOURCE FILE sourceDesc ELEMENT IF APPLICABLE]">
                <bibl>[DESCRIPTION FROM SOURCE FILE IF APPLICABLE]</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>[PROJECT DESCRIPTION BY ELLI/ANDY]</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>[ANY EDITORIAL STATEMENTS BY MASSIMO/ELLI/ANDY]</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <!-- THIS WILL NEED TO BE TWEAKED FOR EACH FILE? WILL CLARIFY
                <refsDecl xml:id="ASLREF">
                <cRefPattern
                matchPattern="(\S+) ([^.]+)\.(.*)"
                replacementPattern="#xpath(//div1[@n='$1']/div2/[@n='$2']//lb[@n='$3'])">
                <p>A reference is created by assembling the following,
                in the reverse order as that listed here:
                <list>
                <item>the <att>n</att> value of the preceding <gi>lb</gi>
                </item>
                <item>a period</item>
                <item>the <att>n</att> value of the ancestor <gi>div2</gi>
                </item>
                <item>a space</item>
                <item>the <att>n</att> value of the parent <gi>div1</gi>
                </item>
                </list>
                </p>
                </cRefPattern>
                </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>
        <!-- NOT SURE ABOUT THESE, WILL TALK TO SYD 
            <encodingDesc>
            <tagsDecl>
            <rendition id="r.head">indent(1)case(allcaps)</rendition>
            <rendition id="r.p">break(yes)pre(¶)</rendition>
            <rendition id="r.trailer">align(center)</rendition>
            <tagUsage gi="trailer" render="r.trailer"></tagUsage>
            <tagUsage gi="p" render="r.p"></tagUsage>
            <tagUsage gi="head" render="r.head"></tagUsage>
            </tagsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>-->
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="1991-11-11">Revised 06/2009 by STG</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
                <div type="section" n="§1" xml:id="sec001">
                    <p>Preamble<anchor type="annotation" n="1" xml:id="legacy1"/></p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec001001" n="1"> I have read, most esteemed Fathers,<anchor type="annotation" n="2" xml:id="legacy2"/> in the records of the Arabians,<anchor type="annotation" n="3" xml:id="legacy3"/> that Abdallah the Saracen<anchor type="annotation" n="4" xml:id="legacy4"/> when questioned as to what, on this stage,
                            so to say, of the world, could be seen most worthy of wonder, replied
                            that there is nothing to be seen more wonderful that man. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec001002" n="2"> In agreement with this opinion is the saying of
                            Hermes: «A great miracle, Asclepius, is man».<anchor type="annotation" n="5" xml:id="legacy5"/>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§2" xml:id="sec002">
                    <p>The current reasons for human pre-eminence are not satisfying</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec002001" n="3"> Still, when I weighed the reasons for these
                            sayings, the numerous considerations advanced by many men to explain the
                            excellence of human nature<anchor type="annotation" n="6" xml:id="legacy6"/> did not
                            fully persuade me: that man is the intermediary between creatures, the
                            familiar of the higher beings, the king of the things beneath him; by
                            the acuteness of his senses, by the inquiry of his reason and by the
                            light of his intelligence the interpreter of nature;<anchor type="annotation" n="7" xml:id="legacy7"/> set midway between fixed eternity and
                            fleeting time and, (as the Persians say)<anchor type="annotation" n="8" xml:id="legacy8"/> the bond, or rather the wedding-song of the world, on David's
                                testimony,<anchor type="annotation" n="9" xml:id="legacy9"/> but little lower that
                            angels. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§3" xml:id="sec003">
                    <p>The final discovery</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec003001" n="4"> These reason are great, nevertheless they are
                            not the principal grounds, that is, those for which man may rightfully
                            claim for himself the privilege of the highest admiration. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec003002" n="5"> Why should we not admire more the angels
                            themselves and the beatific choirs of heaven? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec003003" n="6"> At last, however, it seems to me that I have
                            come to understand why man is the most fortunate of beings and
                            consequently worthy of all admiration, and what finally is the condition
                            which is his lot in the universal order, a condition to be envied not
                            only by brutes but even by the stars and by the intelligences dwelling
                            beyond this world.<anchor type="annotation" n="10" xml:id="legacy10"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec003004" n="7"> A thing surpassing belief and a wondrous one. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec003005" n="8"> Still, why should it not be? For it is on this
                            ground that man is rightly called and considered a great miracle and a
                            living creature worthy of all admiration. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec003006" n="9"> But hear, Fathers, exactly what this condition
                            is and, in the name of your humanity, grant your benign audition to my
                            work. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§4" xml:id="sec004">
                    <p>The history of the creation</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec004001" n="10"> The supreme Father, God the Architect, had
                            already built this cosmic home we behold, the most sacred temple of
                            divinity, according to the laws of the mysterious wisdom. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec004002" n="11"> He had already adorned the supercelestial
                            region with intelligences, quickened the heavely globes with eternal
                            souls and filled the excrementary and filthy parts of the lower world
                            with a multitude of animals of every kind. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec004003" n="12"> But when the work was finished, the Craftsman
                            still longed that there were someone to ponder the meaning of so great a
                            work, to love its beauty, and to wonder at its vastness.<anchor type="annotation" n="11" xml:id="legacy11"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec004004" n="13"> Therefore, when everything was done (as Moses
                            and Timaeus testify), He finally bethought himself of bringing forth
                                man.<anchor type="annotation" n="12" xml:id="legacy12"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec004005" n="14"> But there was not among the archetypes that
                            from which he could fashion a new offspring, nor in his treasure-houses
                            anything which he might bestow on his new son as an inheritance, nor
                            among the seats of the universe any place where the latter might sit to
                            contemplate the universe. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec004006" n="15"> All was now complete; all things had heen
                            assigned to the highest, the middle, and the lowest orders. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec004007" n="16"> But it was not in the nature of the Father's
                            power to fail in his final creation; it was not in the nature of his
                            wisdom to hesitate through lack of counsel in a needful matter, nor it
                            was in the nature of his beneficient love that he who would praise the
                            divine generosity in all other things should be obliged to condemn it in
                            regard to himself. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§5" xml:id="sec005">
                    <p>God's address to man</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec005001" n="17"> At last the best of makers decreed that the
                            creature to whom he had been anable to give anything wholly his own,
                            should have in common whatever belonged to every other being.<anchor type="annotation" n="13" xml:id="legacy13"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec005002" n="18"> He therefore took man, this creature of
                            indeterminate image,<anchor type="annotation" n="14" xml:id="legacy14"/> set him in the
                            middle of the world<anchor type="annotation" n="15" xml:id="legacy15"/> and thus spoke to
                            him: «We have given you, Adam, no fixed seat nor features proper to
                            yourself nor endowment peculiar to you alone, in order that whatever
                            seat, whatever features, whatever endowment you may responsibly desire,
                            these same you may have and possess according to your desire and
                            judgement. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec005003" n="19"> Once defined, the nature of all other beings,
                            is constrained within the laws prescribed by us. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec005004" n="20"> Constrained by no limits, you may determine it
                            for yourself, according to your own free will, in whose hand we have
                            placed you. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec005005" n="21"> I have placed you at the world's center so
                            that you may thence more easily look around atwhatever is in the world. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec005006" n="22"> We have made you neither of heaven nor of
                            earth, neither mortal nor immortal,<anchor type="annotation" n="16" xml:id="legacy16"/> so
                            that you may, as the free and extraordinary<anchor type="annotation" n="17" xml:id="legacy17"/> shaper of yourself, fashion yourself in the form you will
                            prefer. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec005007" n="23"> It will be in your power to degenerate into
                            the lower forms of life, which are brutish; you shall have the power,
                            according to your soul's judgement, to be reborn into the higher orders,
                            which are divine». </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§6" xml:id="sec006">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec006001" n="24"> O supreme liberality<anchor type="annotation" n="18" xml:id="legacy18"/> of God the Father and wonderful happiness<anchor type="annotation" n="19" xml:id="legacy19"/> of man! </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006002" n="25"> To him is given to be what he desires and what
                            he wills.<anchor type="annotation" n="20" xml:id="legacy20"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006003" n="26"> As soon as they are born, brutes bring with
                            them “from their mother’s womb,”<anchor type="annotation" n="21" xml:id="legacy21"/> as
                            Lucilius says, all that they are going to possess. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006004" n="27"> Superior spirits have been, either from the
                            beginning or soon after, that which they are perpetually going to be
                            throughout eternity. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006005" n="28"> The Father infused in man, at birth, every
                            sort of seed and sprouts of every kind of life.<anchor type="annotation" n="22" xml:id="legacy22"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006006" n="29"> These seeds will grow and bear their fruit in
                            each man who will cultivate them. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006007" n="30"> If he cultivates his vegetable seeds, he will
                            become a plant. If he cultivates his sensitive seeds, he will become
                            brutish. If he cultivates his rational seeds, he will become a heavenly
                            animal. If he cultivates his intellectual seeds, he will be an angel and
                            a son of God.<anchor type="annotation" n="23" xml:id="legacy23"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec006008" n="31"> And if he is not contented with the fate of
                            any creature, he will gather himself into the center of his own unity
                            and, become one spirit with God, will join the solitary darkness<anchor type="annotation" n="24" xml:id="legacy24"/> of the Father, who is above all things,
                            and will stand ahead of all things. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§7" xml:id="sec007">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec007001" n="32"> Who will not wonder at this chameleon?<anchor type="annotation" n="25" xml:id="legacy25"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec007002" n="33"> Or rather, who will admire any other being
                            more? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec007003" n="34"> Not without reasons, Asclepius the
                                Athenian<anchor type="annotation" n="26" xml:id="legacy26"/> said that in the secret
                            rites he [man] was symbolized by Proteus, because of his changing and
                            metamorphous nature.<anchor type="annotation" n="27" xml:id="legacy27"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec007004" n="35"> Hence the metamorphoses celebrated among the
                                Jews<anchor type="annotation" n="28" xml:id="legacy28"/> and the Pythagoreans.<anchor type="annotation" n="29" xml:id="legacy29"/>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§8" xml:id="sec008">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec008001" n="36"> Indeed, even the most secret Hebrew theology
                            at one time transforms holy Enoch into an angel of divinity, whom they
                            call metatron, and at other times it reshapes other men into other
                                spirits.<anchor type="annotation" n="30" xml:id="legacy30"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec008002" n="37"> According to Pythagoreans, wicked men are
                            deformed into brutes, and if you believe Empedocles, into plants as
                                well.<anchor type="annotation" n="31" xml:id="legacy31"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec008003" n="38"> Imitating them, Mohammed often repeated that
                            he who strays from divine law becomes a brute. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec008004" n="39"> Indeed, it is not the bark which makes the
                            plant, but dull and non-sentient nature; not the hide which makes a
                            horse or other beast of burden, but a brutal and sensual soul; not the
                            circular body which makes the heaven(s), but right reason; not the
                            separation from the body which makes the angel, but spiritual
                            intelligence. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec008005" n="40"> If you see someone, a slave to his belly,
                            crawling on the ground, it is not a man you see but a plant; if you see
                            someone who, as though blinded by Calipso with empty imaginations, under
                            a seductive spell, is enslaved by his senses, it a brute you see, not a
                            man. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec008006" n="41"> If you see a philosopher discerning things
                            with right reason, worship him; he is a heavenly not an earthly animal. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec008007" n="42"> If you see a pure contemplator, oblivious to
                            his body, absorbed in the recesses of the mind, this is neither an
                            earthly nor a heavenly animal: this is a superior spirit, clothed with
                            human flesh. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§9" xml:id="sec009">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec009001" n="43"> Who, then, will not admire man? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec009002" n="44"> Not undeservedly, in the Mosaic and Christian
                            Scriptures he is called at times with the name of every flesh, at times
                            of every creature, for he fashions, shapes and transforms<anchor type="annotation" n="32" xml:id="legacy32"/> his own look into that of every flesh,
                            his own mind into that of every creature.<anchor type="annotation" n="33" xml:id="legacy33"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec009003" n="45"> Accordingly, Evantes the Persian, explaining
                            Chaldaean theology, writes that no inner image belongs to man, but many
                            exterior and derived ones.<anchor type="annotation" n="34" xml:id="legacy34"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec009004" n="46"> Hence that saying of the Chaldaens that man is
                            animal by nature, diverse, multiform and inconstant. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§10" xml:id="sec010">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec010001" n="47"> Yet, what is the reason of all this? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec010002" n="48"> It is in order for us to understand that,
                            because we were born with the option to be what we want to be, we must
                            take most care of this; lest people say of us that, being held in honor,
                            we did not realize that we reduced ourselves to brutes and mindless
                            beasts of burden. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec010003" n="49"> Let us rather remember the saying of Asaph the
                            prophet: “You are all gods and sons of the most high,”<anchor type="annotation" n="35" xml:id="legacy35"/> unless abusing the most indulgent
                            liberality of the Father, we turn from beneficial to harmful the free
                            choice he bestowed on us. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec010004" n="50"> Let a holy ambition pervade our soul, so that,
                            not satisfied with mediocre things, we strive for the loftiest and apply
                            ourselves with all our strength to pursue them (because we can achieve
                            them, if we want). </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec010005" n="51"> . Let us spurn earthly things, disregard the
                                celestial,<anchor type="annotation" n="36" xml:id="legacy36"/> and reject all that is
                            of this world, in order to fly to the otherwordly court near the most
                            eminent divinity. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec010006" n="52"> There, as sacred mysteries reveal, Seraphim,
                            Cherubim and Thrones occupy the first places; let us emulate their
                            dignity and glory, unwilling as we are to yield to them and unable to
                            endure second place. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec010007" n="53"> If so we wish, we will not be at all inferior
                            to them. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§11" xml:id="sec011">
                    <p>The Nature of the Highest Angels</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec011001" n="54"> But in what way, or by doing what? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011002" n="55"> Let us see what they do, what life they lead. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011003" n="56"> If we live that life (and indeed we can), we
                            will be equal to their lot. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011004" n="57"> The Seraph burns with the fire of love; the
                            Cherub shines with the splendor of intelligence; the Throne stands in
                            the steadfastness of judgment. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011005" n="58"> Therefore if we, being dedicated to an active
                            life, undertake the care of inferior things with proper consideration of
                            their worth, we will be strengthened by the steadfast solidity of the
                            Thrones. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011006" n="59"> If we, being unburdened by actions, meditate
                            on the Creator in His creation and on creation in the Creator, we will
                            be engaged in the tranquillity of contemplation; we will shine on all
                            sides with Cherubic light. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011007" n="60"> If we burn for the Creator alone, with
                            charity, with its all-consuming fire, we will burst into flame in the
                            likeness of the Seraphim<anchor type="annotation" n="37" xml:id="legacy37"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011008" n="61"> Upon the Throne, that is upon the just judge,
                            sits God, the Judge of all time. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011009" n="62"> Over the Cherub, that is over the
                            contemplator, He flies and, almost brooding over him<anchor type="annotation" n="38" xml:id="legacy38"/>, imbues him with warmth. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011010" n="63"> Indeed, the Spirit of the Lord is carried over
                            the waters, the waters that, it is said, are above the Heavens and that
                            praise God in the pre-dawn hymns in the book of Job<anchor type="annotation" n="39" xml:id="legacy39"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011011" n="64"> And the Seraph, that is the lover, is in God
                            and God is in him; and God and he are one. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec011012" n="65"> Great is the power of the Thrones that we may
                            reach by judging; supreme is the height of the Seraphim that we may
                            reach by loving. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§12" xml:id="sec012">
                    <p>The Angels As Inspiration to Man</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec012001" n="66"> And yet in what manner can anyone either judge
                            or love things unknown? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012002" n="67"> Moses loved the Lord Whom he saw and, as a
                            judge, he administered to the people the things that he earlier saw on
                            the mountain as a contemplator. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012003" n="68"> Hence the Cherub, located in the middle
                            position, prepares us for the Seraphic fire and likewise illuminates us
                            for the judgment of the Thrones. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012004" n="69"> This is the bond of the First Minds, the order
                            of Pallas, the guardian of contemplative philosophy. First we must
                            emulate him, thirst after him and to the same degree understand him in
                            order that we may be raised to the heights of love and descend well
                            taught and prepared to the duties of action. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012005" n="70"> And so it is valuable, if our life is to be
                            modeled on the example of the Cherubs' life, to have before our eyes an
                            idea of what their life is and what it is like, what their actions are
                            and what works are theirs. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012006" n="71"> Because we, who are flesh and know only
                            earthly things, are not permitted to follow their model of our own
                            accord, let us consult the ancient Fathers for they, to whom these
                            things were common and well known, can provide us with certain and
                            abundant evidence of its nature. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012007" n="72"> Let us inquire of the apostle Paul, the chosen
                            vessel, about the activities of the Cherubic hosts that he saw when
                            raised up to the third heaven. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec012008" n="73"> He will certainly answer, according to the
                            interpretation of Dionysius, that they are cleansed, then illuminated
                            and afterwards are perfected. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§13" xml:id="sec013">
                    <p>The Preparation of the Soul</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec013001" n="74"> We, emulating the Cherubic life on Earth,
                            curbing the drive of the emotions through moral science, dispersing the
                            darkness of reason through dialectic (as if washing away the squalor of
                            ignorance and vices), therefore purge our souls lest our emotions run
                            amok or our reason imprudently run off course at any time. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec013002" n="75"> Then well we imbue our purified and prepared
                            soul with the light of natural philosophy so that afterwards we may
                            perfect it with the knowledge of divine things. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§14" xml:id="sec014">
                    <p>Jacob's Ladder</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec014001" n="76"> And lest our Fathers be enough for us, let us
                            consult Jacob the patriarch whose image shines, chiseled in the dwelling
                            place of glory. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec014002" n="77"> The most wise father, asleep in the lower
                            world and awake in the higher, will illumine us<anchor type="annotation" n="40" xml:id="legacy40"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec014003" n="78"> But he will teach us through a figure (in this
                            way all things were known to them) that there is a ladder which
                            stretches from the lowest earth to the highest Heavens and that is
                            marked by a series of many rungs. God is at its height and the
                            contemplative angels move up and down it in turns. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§15" xml:id="sec015">
                    <p>Our Approach to Jacob's Ladder</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec015001" n="79"> So, if we are to carry out these things in our
                            efforts to imitate the angelic life, who, I ask, will dare to touch the
                            Ladder of God, either with an unclean foot or with unwashed hands? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015002" n="80"> As the mysteries have it, it is unlawful to
                            touch the clean with the unclean. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015003" n="81"> But what feet are these? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015004" n="82"> What hands? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015005" n="83"> To be sure, the foot of the soul is that part
                            which is most despicable, that which leans upon matter as if on earthly
                            soil; it is the faculty, I say, that feeds and nourishes, I say, the
                            kindling wood of lust and the teacher of sensual weakness<anchor type="annotation" n="41" xml:id="legacy41"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015006" n="84"> And why not call the hands of the soul its
                            irascible part, that which fights on behalf of desire, battles for it
                            and like a plunderer takes away in broad daylight and the public arena
                            the things that desire, resting in the shade, then devours? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015007" n="85"> These hands, these feet, are the entire
                            sensual part of the body in which resides the attraction that holds the
                            soul back, as they say, obtorto collo. Let us wash them in moral
                            philosophy like in a flowing river lest we be held back from the ladder
                            as wicked and unclean. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015008" n="86"> And yet not even this will be enough if we
                            wish to be companions to the angels who hasten up and down Jacob's
                            ladder unless we are first well prepared and instructed to be promoted
                            from step to step, to wheel away nowhere from the course of the ladder,
                            and to encounter the reciprocal movements. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec015009" n="87"> Once we, inspired by the Cherubic spirit, have
                            reached this point through the art of speaking or of reasoning, that is,
                            philosophizing according to the grades of Nature, penetrating the whole
                            from the center to the center, we will then descend, dashing the one
                            into many with Titanic force like Osiris, and ascend, drawing together
                            with Apollonian force the many into one like Osiris' limbs<anchor type="annotation" n="42" xml:id="legacy42"/> until at last, resting in the bosom of
                            the Father Who is at the top of the ladder, we will be made perfect in
                            theological bliss. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§16" xml:id="sec016">
                    <p>Peace and the Dual Nature of the Soul</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec016001" n="88"> And let us inquire with just Job, who entered
                            into a pact of life with the God of life before he was brought into
                                being<anchor type="annotation" n="43" xml:id="legacy43"/>, as to what God the Highest
                            desires among those tens of hundreds of thousands who are there present
                            before Him: he will certainly answer peace, in accordance with that
                            which is written in Job: «He who makes peace in the heavens». </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec016002" n="89"> And since the middle order interprets the
                            precepts of the highest order for the lower ones, let now Empedocles the
                            philosopher interpret for us the words of Job the theologian. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec016003" n="90"> Empedocles, as his songs attest, presents to
                            us through the symbols of conflict and friendship, or of war and peace,
                            the dual nature that is set in our souls: one of them lifts us upwards
                            to the heavens and the other drags us down into the depths. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec016004" n="91"> In these songs he deplores being tossed into
                            the depths, driven by conflict and discord like a madman and banished
                            from the gods<anchor type="annotation" n="44" xml:id="legacy44"/>. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§17" xml:id="sec017">
                    <p>Theology As Succor for the Soul Fraught with Strife</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec017001" n="92"> Manifold indeed, Oh Fathers, is the discord in
                            us; we grave internal, more than civil, wars in our home. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017002" n="93"> They are such that, if we desire them not, if
                            we yearn after that peace which will lift us up and set us among God's
                            most exalted ones, only moral philosophy will be able to still the
                            troubles within us and bring us calm. If in our inner self we greatly
                            desire above all else a truce from our enemies, we will beat down the
                            unbridled stampede of the manifold beast, the aggression, ire and
                            arrogance of the lion<anchor type="annotation" n="45" xml:id="legacy45"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017003" n="94"> Then, if thinking rightly, we yearn for the
                            safety of perpetual peace for ourselves, it will come and liberally
                            satisfy our desires; indeed, both beasts having been sacrificed like a
                            stuck sow<anchor type="annotation" n="46" xml:id="legacy46"/>, it will ratify an
                            everlasting pact of the most holy peace between the flesh and the
                            spirit. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017004" n="95"> Dialectic will calm the tumults of reason
                            agitated and tossed about between the contradictions of speech and the
                            captiousness of syllogism. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017005" n="96"> Natural philosophy will allay the differences
                            of opinion and disagreements which from all sides vex, perplex and
                            afflict our restless soul. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017006" n="97"> But it will bring harmony in such a way as to
                            remind us that nature is the offspring of war, as Heraclitus said, and
                            for this reason it is called by Homer «contention». </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017007" n="98"> For this reason it is said that in philosophy
                            true rest and stable peace cannot reveal themselves to us alone, that
                            this is the duty and privilege of its mistress, that is, of the most
                            holy theology. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec017008" n="99"> She will show us the way to this peace and
                            like a companion will lead us. Seeing us hurrying along from afar, she
                            will call out, «Come to me, you who exert yourselves in vain; come and I
                            will restore you; come to me and I will give you that peace which the
                            world and nature cannot give to you». </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§18" xml:id="sec018">
                    <p>The Soul's Search for Peace and Its Union with God</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec018001" n="100"> So gently called, so kindly invited, we will
                            then fly away into the embrace of the most blessed Mother like
                            terrestrial Mercuries with winged feet; thoroughly will we enjoy the
                            longed-for peace. This is that most holy peace, the indissoluble bond,
                            the harmonious friendship in which all souls, in one mind, a Mind that
                            is above all minds, are not only in agreement but indeed, in a certain
                            ineffable way, inwardly become one<anchor type="annotation" n="47" xml:id="legacy47"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec018002" n="101"> This is that friendship which the
                            Pythagoreans call the end of all philosophy, that peace which God makes
                            in His heavens, which the angels who came down to earth announced to men
                            of good will so that these men would, ascending to heaven, be
                            transformed by it into angels. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec018003" n="102"> Let us desire this peace for our friends, for
                            our times; let us desire it for whatever home we enter. Let us desire it
                            for our soul so that in it may be made a house of the Lord, so that,
                            after casting off its impurities through moral philosophy and dialectic,
                            our soul may adorn itself with multi-faceted philosophy, as if with
                            royal magnificence, may crown the heights of her doors with the garlands
                            of theology, and finally so that the King of Glory may descend, together
                            with the Father, to make a home in it. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec018004" n="103"> If our soul shows herself to be worthy of
                            such a Guest (for immense is His Clemency) clad in gold, like a wedding
                            toga, surrounded by a diverse variety of sciences, she will receive Him
                            not as a Guest but as a Bridegroom. She will wish to be separated from
                            her people so as not to be separated from Him. Having forgotten her own
                            father's home, indeed, having forgotten herself, she will wish to die in
                            herself that she may live in her Spouse in Whose sight the death of His
                            saints is truly precious. This is the death, I say, if one must call
                            that plenitude of life death, whose contemplation is, according to the
                            sages, the study of philosophy<anchor type="annotation" n="48" xml:id="legacy48"/>. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§19" xml:id="sec019">
                    <p>Moses' Allegory of the Tabernacle</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec019001" n="104"> Let us take as an example Moses, himself just
                            a bit inferior to the fountainlike fullness of sacrosanct and ineffable
                            intelligence whose nectar inebriates the angels<anchor type="annotation" n="49" xml:id="legacy49"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec019002" n="105"> We will hear the venerable Judge thus declare
                            His laws to us who live in the empty solitude of this body: «Let those
                            who are unclean and as yet in need of moral philosophy dwell with the
                            masses outside the tabernacle in the open air while they purify
                            themselves like the priests of Thessaly. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec019003" n="106"> Let those who have already put their behavior
                            in order and have been received into the sanctuary not let lay hands
                            upon the sacred things but first, in the service of dialectic, let them
                            serve the holy things of philosophy like diligent Levites. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec019004" n="107"> Once they are allowed access to the holy
                            things in the priesthood of philosophy, let them contemplate the
                            multicolored aspect of the higher kingdom of God, that is, the divine,
                            princely decoration, as well as the celestial candelabra adorned with
                            seven lights. Let them behold the skins so that they, permitted at last
                            into the recesses of the temple through the merits of theological
                            sublimity, may rejoice in the glory of the Divinity without any veil of
                            a likeness coming in between» <anchor type="annotation" n="50" xml:id="legacy50"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec019005" n="108"> These things Moses truly commands of us and
                            in commanding instructs, incites and encourages so that through
                            philosophy we may prepare for ourselves, while we are able, the path to
                            the future celestial glory. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§20" xml:id="sec020">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec020001" n="109"> In fact, however, not only the Mosaic and
                            Christian mysteries,<anchor type="annotation" n="51" xml:id="legacy51"/> but also the
                            theology of the ancients<anchor type="annotation" n="52" xml:id="legacy52"/> show us the
                            dignity and value of the liberal arts which I am about to discuss. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020002" n="110"> For at what else was the observance of the
                            different degrees of initiation in Greek mysteries aimed? Only after
                            having been purified through the arts which we might call expiatory,
                            moral philosophy and dialectic,<anchor type="annotation" n="53" xml:id="legacy53"/> the
                            initiates could gain entrance to the mysteries.<anchor type="annotation" n="54" xml:id="legacy54"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020003" n="111"> And what else can such admission possibly
                            signify if not an interpretation by means of philosophy of the most
                            hidden nature? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020004" n="112"> At this point they were finally prepared for
                            the coming of <figure>
                                <graphic url="epopteia.gif"/>
                            </figure>,<anchor type="annotation" n="55" xml:id="legacy55"/> that is the intimate vision
                            of divine things by the light of theology. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020005" n="113"> Who would not long to be initiated into such
                            sacred rites? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020006" n="114"> Who would not desire, putting aside all human
                            concerns, despising the goods of fortune and neglecting the body, to
                            become a guest at the table of the gods while still living on earth,
                            and, soaked in the nectar of eternity, to receive, though still a mortal
                            animal, the gift of immortality? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020007" n="115"> Who would not wish to be so inspired by the
                            Socratic frenzies that Plato celebrates in the Phaedrus, that he is
                            transferred after a quick course, fleeing readily with oarlike strokes
                            of wings and feet, from here (that is, from this world set on evil) to
                            the heavenly Jerusalem? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020008" n="116"> We shall be led away, Fathers, we shall be
                            led away by the Socratic frenzies,<anchor type="annotation" n="56" xml:id="legacy56"/>
                            which will so lift us out of our mind as to put our mind and ourselves
                            in God. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020009" n="117"> We shall be led away by them, however, only
                            if we ourselves first complete that which is ours to do; for, if through
                            moral philosophy the forces of our passions have been correctly attuned,
                            in the correct proportions, based on harmonic measure, so as to be tuned
                            one to the other in lasting consonance; and if, through dialectic, our
                            reason has progressed by measured advance, only then, stirred by the
                            frenzy of the Muses, we shall drink the heavenly harmony with our inmost
                            hearing. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020010" n="118"> Then Bacchus, the leader of the Muses,<anchor type="annotation" n="57" xml:id="legacy57"/> through his mysteries (that is, through
                            the visible signs of nature) will show us, who philosophize, the
                            invisible things of God, and will make us drunk with the abundance of
                            God's house, in which, if we prove entirely faithful, like Moses, most
                            sacred theology shall draw close to us, animating us with redoubled
                            frenzy. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec020011" n="119"> For we, raised to her most eminent height,
                            thence comparing to indivisible eternity all things that are and shall
                            be and have been and admiring their primeval beauty, shall be the
                            Phoebean seers; of this beauty we shall become the winged lovers. And at
                            last, roused by ineffable love as if by a sting, and borne outside
                            ourselves like burning Seraphim, filled with the godhead, we shall be no
                            longer ourselves, but He Himself Who made us. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§21" xml:id="sec021">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec021001" n="120"> The sacred names of Apollo, if anyone
                            investigates their meanings and hidden mysteries, sufficiently show that
                            that God is, no less than a seer, a philosopher. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec021002" n="121"> But since Ammonius<anchor type="annotation" n="58" xml:id="legacy58"/> has amply examined this matter, there is no reason for me
                            to treat it further; but, Fathers, let us recall the three Delphic
                                precepts,<anchor type="annotation" n="59" xml:id="legacy59"/> which are absolutely
                            necessary to those who are to enter the most holy and august temple, not
                            of the false, but of the true Apollo who lighteth every soul that cometh
                            into this world; you will realize that they exhort us to nothing else
                            but to embrace with all our strength the tripartite philosophy that we
                            now discuss. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec021003" n="122"> For the famous maxim, <figure>
                                <graphic url="meden.gif"/>
                            </figure>(that is: «Nothing too much»), rightly prescribes as rule and
                            norm for every virtue the criterion of the "mean", of which moral
                            philosophy speaks. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec021004" n="123"> Then the maxim, <figure>
                                <graphic url="gnothi.gif"/>
                            </figure> (that is: «Know thyself»), urges and exhorts us to the
                            knowledge of all nature, of which the nature of man is the intermediate
                            and, so to speak, the mixture. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec021005" n="124"> For he who knows himself, in himself knows
                            all things, as first Zoroaster wrote, and later Plato in the Alcibiades. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec021006" n="125"> Finally, once natural philosophy has
                            enlightened us with this knowledge, and we, being very close to God and
                            saying <figure>
                                <graphic url="ei.gif"/>
                            </figure> (that is: «You are»), we shall address by a theological
                            salutation the true Apollo on intimate and likewise blissful terms. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§22" xml:id="sec022">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec022001" n="126"> But let us also consult Pythagoras,<anchor type="annotation" n="60" xml:id="legacy60"/> the wisest of men, and wise precisely
                            because he never deemed himself worthy of that name.<anchor type="annotation" n="61" xml:id="legacy61"/>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022002" n="127"> He will firstly advise us «not to sit on a
                            bushel», that is, not to lose, abandoning it to sloth and inaction, that
                            rational part by which the soul measures, judges and considers all
                            things; but rather, by the exercise and the rule of dialectic, to direct
                            and to stimulate it unremittingly. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022003" n="128"> Then he will point out to us two things to be
                            avoided above all: that is, making water facing the sun and cutting our
                            nails while offering sacrifice. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022004" n="129"> But after we have evacuated the lax appetites
                            of our too-abundant pleasures through moral philosophy, and pared away,
                            like nails, the sharp points of wrath and the claws of animosity, only
                            then shall we finally begin to take part in the sacred rites, that is,
                            in the above mentioned mysteries of Bacchus, and to dedicate ourselves
                            to that contemplation of which the sun is rightly named the father and
                            the guide. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022005" n="130"> Finally Pythagoras will exhort us «to feed
                            the cock», that is, to nourish the divine part of the soul with the
                            knowledge of divine things, as if with substantial food and heavenly
                            ambrosia. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022006" n="131"> This is the cock whose glance the lion, that
                            is, all earthly power, holds in fear and awe. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022007" n="132"> This the cock to whom, we read in Job,
                            intelligence was given. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022008" n="133"> When this cock crows, erring man comes to his
                            senses. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022009" n="134"> This cock in the morning twilight joins his
                            voice every day to the lauds that morning stars raise to God. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec022010" n="135"> This is the cock which Socrates, at the hour
                            of his death, when he hoped to join the divine of his soul to the
                            divinity of a greater world, said that he owed to Aesculapius, that is,
                            to the physician of souls, now that he was beyond danger of any bodily
                            illness. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§23" xml:id="sec023">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec023001" n="136"> But let us review also the records of the
                                Chaldeans,<anchor type="annotation" n="62" xml:id="legacy62"/> and we shall see (if
                            they are to be trusted) that the arts that open for mortals the road to
                            happiness are the same. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023002" n="137"> The Chaldean interpreters write that it was a
                            saying of Zoroaster's that the soul is winged and that, when the wings
                            fall from her, she is plunged into the body; but she flies back to
                            heaven when the wings grow again. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023003" n="138"> When his disciples asked him in what manner
                            they could obtain souls with well-plumed wings and able to fly, he
                            replied: «Wet them well in the waters of life». </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023004" n="139"> And when they asked him again where they
                            might obtain these waters, he answered them by a parable (as was his
                            custom): «God's paradise is purified and watered by four rivers. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023005" n="140"> From these you may draw the waters that will
                            save you. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023006" n="141"> The name of the river which flows from the
                            north is [q-s-t], which means the right; that which flows from the west
                            is named [k-?-r-n], which means expiation; that which comes from the
                            east is named [n-h-r] , that is light, while that from the south is
                            [r-h-m-n-t], which may be translated as piety». </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023007" n="142"> Now consider carefully and with full
                            attention, Fathers, what these doctrines of Zoroaster aim at: surely at
                            nothing else than inducing us to wash away, by moral science, as by
                            Iberian ways, the uncleanness from our eyes; and to rectify our gaze by
                            dialectic, as if by the northern line. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023008" n="143"> Then we should become accustomed, in the
                            contemplation of nature, to endure the still feeble light of truth, as
                            if it were the first rays of the rising sun, so that through theological
                            piety and the most holy worship of God, we become able finally to
                            endure, like the eagles of heaven, the dazzling splendor of the meridian
                            sun. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023009" n="144"> These are, perhaps, those celebrated morning,
                            midday and evening thoughts first sung by David and then given a larger
                            explanation by Augustine. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023010" n="145"> This is the noonday light that directly
                            inflames the Seraphim and equally illuminates the Cherubim. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023011" n="146"> This is the country towards which our ancient
                            father Abraham was ever advancing. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023012" n="147"> This is the region where, according to the
                            doctrines of the Cabalists and the Arabs, there is no place for unclean
                            spirits. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023013" n="148"> And, if it may be permitted, even in the form
                            of a riddle, to bring anything at all of the most hidden mysteries into
                            the open,<anchor type="annotation" n="63" xml:id="legacy63"/> since the sudden fall from
                            heaven has condemned the head of man to dizziness and, according to
                            Jeremiah, death has come in through the windows to smite our livers and
                            breasts, let us call upon Raphael,<anchor type="annotation" n="64" xml:id="legacy64"/> the
                            heavenly physician, that he may release us by moral philosophy and
                            dialectic, as though by healing drugs. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec023014" n="149"> Then, when we are restored to health,
                            Gabriel, the strength of God, will abide in us and, leading us through
                            the marvels of nature and showing us the merit and the power of God
                            everywhere, he will finally deliver us to the high priest Michael, who
                            in turn will adorn us, who have completed our service to philosophy,
                            with the insignia of theological priesthood, as with a crown of precious
                            stones. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§24" xml:id="sec024">
                    <p>On the way the contemporary conception of philosophy differs from mine</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec024001" n="150"> These are the reasons, most reverend fathers,
                            which have not only encouraged<anchor type="annotation" n="65" xml:id="legacy65"/> me but
                            even invested me with the duty of studying philosophy<anchor type="annotation" n="66" xml:id="legacy66"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec024002" n="151"> And I was certainly not going to expound
                            them, except to answer those who are accustomed to condemning the study
                            of philosophy, especially among men of high rank, or more generally, in
                            men of a certain fortune<anchor type="annotation" n="67" xml:id="legacy67"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec024003" n="152"> For this whole philosophizing is now (and
                            this is the misfortune of our age) considered with contempt and
                                insulted<anchor type="annotation" n="68" xml:id="legacy68"/>, rather than being
                            occasion for honor and glory. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec024004" n="153"> Thus this deadly and monstrous persuasion has
                            much invaded the minds of almost everybody - so that either no one or
                            few persons must philosophize<anchor type="annotation" n="69" xml:id="legacy69"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec024005" n="154"> As if it were a thing of very little worth to
                            have before our eyes and at our hands, with the evidence resulting from
                            the most accurate research<anchor type="annotation" n="70" xml:id="legacy70"/>, the causes
                            of things, the ways of nature, the reason of the universe, the plans of
                            God, the mysteries of heaven and earth, unless by it one may avidly seek
                            after some favor or procure a profit for oneself. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec024006" n="155"> Rather, we lowered ourselves to the point
                            (and it's such a sorrow) that now those only are considered wise who
                            reduce philosophy<anchor type="annotation" n="71" xml:id="legacy71"/> to a
                                merchandise<anchor type="annotation" n="72" xml:id="legacy72"/>. This would be like
                                seeing<anchor type="annotation" n="73" xml:id="legacy73"/> the chaste Pallas, who
                            dwells among men by a gift of the gods, rejected, chased out, whistled
                            at in scorn, and with no one to love her, no one to protect<anchor type="annotation" n="74" xml:id="legacy74"/> her unless she, as a prostitute who has
                                accepted<anchor type="annotation" n="75" xml:id="legacy75"/> a pittance for her
                            deflowered virginity<anchor type="annotation" n="76" xml:id="legacy76"/>, pays back into
                            the pocket<anchor type="annotation" n="77" xml:id="legacy77"/> of her love the
                            ill-procured money. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§25" xml:id="sec025">
                    <p>Personal statement on the value and the meaning of philosophy</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec025001" n="156"> And I say all these things (not without the
                            deepest grief and indignation) not against the princes, but against the
                            philosophers of this age, who are convinced and openly declare that no
                            one should pursue philosophy for the reason that there is no recompense
                            for philosophers, no prizes awarded them. And they say so, although they
                            show evidently by this one word that they are not true philosophers. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec025002" n="157"> Therefore, since their whole life has been
                            dedicated to money-making and ambition, they are unable to embrace the
                            knowledge of truth for its own sake. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec025003" n="158"> This much shall I grant to myself (and I
                            shall not blush at all for praising myself in this respect) that I have
                            never philosophized for any other reason than for the sake of being a
                            philosopher, nor have I ever hoped or sought from my studies, from my
                            watches, any reward or fruit other than the nourishment of my mind and
                            the knowledge of the truth, always so greatly desired by me<anchor type="annotation" n="78" xml:id="legacy78"/>. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec025004" n="159"> And I have always been so avid for it and so
                            enamored of it that, setting aside all private and public concerns, I
                            devoted my whole self to the leisure of contemplation<anchor type="annotation" n="79" xml:id="legacy79"/>, from which no calumny of the envious
                            persons, no slander of the enemies of wisdom have been able to divert me
                            so far, nor will it be able in the future. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec025005" n="160"> Philosophy herself has taught me to rely on
                            my own conscience rather than on the judgments of others, and always to
                            consider not so much how to avoid with my behavior that people speak
                            badly of me, as, rather, how not to say or do myself anything evil. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§26" xml:id="sec026">
                    <p>On the list of the accusations and the attitude of defense without
                        resentment</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec026001" n="161"> In fact, most reverend fathers, I was not
                            unaware that this disputation proposal of mine<anchor type="annotation" n="80" xml:id="legacy80"/>, would reveal itself as grateful and enjoyable to all you,
                            who favor the good arts and have been willing to honor this discussion
                            with your very authoritative presence, as it would be, on the contrary,
                            troublesome and unpleasant to many others. I am also aware that there is
                            no lack of those who criticize my undertaking; that they have done so
                            previously and continue to do so for various reasons. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec026002" n="162"> Sincere and holy actions aimed at the
                            attainment of virtue have been known to have at least as many, if not
                            more critics<anchor type="annotation" n="81" xml:id="legacy81"/>, as those wicked and
                            unjust actions perpetrated in the interest of perversion. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec026003" n="163"> There are, undeniably, those who disapprove
                            of this field of discussion as well as this particular use of public
                            debate, maintaining that they serve more as an ostentatious form of
                            displaying intelligence than an attempt to increase one's own knowledge. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec026004" n="164"> There are also those who in truth do not
                            scorn this kind of exercise; neither do they approve of it in me,
                            however, since at a mere age of twenty-three years, I have dared to
                            propose a discussion on the sublime mysteries of Christian theology, the
                            most grueling questions of philosophy and of unexplored fields of
                            knowledge, in a famous city, before a vast assembly of learned men, in
                            the presence of the apostolic senate. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec026005" n="165"> Still others, although they allow me the
                            right to debate, do not wish to grant me the permission to dispute nine
                            hundred theses, deeming the task and my desire to participate in it as
                            superfluous and unnecessary as beyond my intellectual powers. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec026006" n="166"> I would surrender readily to their reproach,
                            had I been so taught by the philosophy which I profess; nor should I
                            attempt to respond to it, as my philosophy also teaches, if I believed
                            that this discussion had been initiated with the purpose of litigation. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec026007" n="167"> Therefore, we shall set aside any intention
                            of hostile provocation<anchor type="annotation" n="82" xml:id="legacy82"/>, ridding our
                            own souls of that resentment and spite which Plato assures us to be
                            nonexistent in the rank of the Gods. Let us then amiably decide whether
                            I am to begin this discussion, and whether I should entertain so large a
                            number of theses. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§27" xml:id="sec027">
                    <p>Response to the first order of accusations</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec027001" n="168"> Firstly, I shall say very little by way of
                            response to those who maliciously criticize this use of public
                            disputation. It is a crime, if we must call it so, that has been
                            committed on numerous occasions not only by me and by all of you,
                            eminent doctors, who have partaken quite often in it and not without
                            high honor and praise, but also by Plato, Aristotle, and all the most
                            revered philosophers of every age. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec027002" n="169"> And these men were certain that, in order to
                            arrive at the knowledge for which they searched, wholehearted engagement
                            in rigorous public debate was imperative. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec027003" n="170"> In fact, just as the body's muscles become
                            robust through gymnastics, so undoubtedly, in this literary gymnasium of
                            sorts, the forces of the soul and the mind become firm and vigorous. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec027004" n="171"> I have come to believe that the message of
                            the poets, in their singing of the arms of Pallas, and of the Hebrews in
                            calling <figure>
                                <graphic url="brzl.gif"/>
                            </figure><anchor type="annotation" n="83" xml:id="legacy83"/>, or the sword the symbol of
                            wise men, cannot be other than that this honorable pursuit of public
                            debate is absolutely necessary in the attainment of wisdom. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec027005" n="172"> Perhaps it is this principle that influenced
                            the Chaldeans' hope that, in the horoscope<anchor type="annotation" n="84" xml:id="legacy84"/> of one who was to become a philosopher, Mars would behold
                            Mercury from three separate angles<anchor type="annotation" n="85" xml:id="legacy85"/>; it
                            is almost as if philosophy, in the absence of all these contests and
                            encounters, would become sluggish and dormant. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§28" xml:id="sec028">
                    <p>Reply to the second accusation</p>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec028001" n="173"> It is more difficult for me, though, to
                            defend myself against those who pronounce me unequal to this
                            undertaking; in fact, it seems that in pronouncing myself equal to it, I
                            shall be branded with judgments of immodesty and an excessively high
                            opinion of myself. If, instead, I admit that I am unequal to it, I shall
                            be charged with recklessness and imprudence. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028002" n="174"> So you see the difficulties into which I have
                                run<anchor type="annotation" n="86" xml:id="legacy86"/>, the situation in which I am
                                placed<anchor type="annotation" n="87" xml:id="legacy87"/>, since I cannot without
                            blame promise about myself that which I must then fulfill without blame. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028003" n="175"> I can refer, perhaps, to Job's famous
                                saying<anchor type="annotation" n="88" xml:id="legacy88"/>, that the spirit exists in
                            all men; and find comfort in what Timothy was told: ìLet no man despise
                            thy young age.î </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028004" n="176"> To speak, though, from my own conscience, I
                            could say<anchor type="annotation" n="89" xml:id="legacy89"/> with all sincerity that
                            there is nothing great or singular in me. While I strongly uphold my own
                            eager commitment to the good sciences, I do not attribute myself nor
                            expect the title of scholar. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028005" n="177"> To he who may ask how and why I have
                            encumbered myself with so heavy a burden, I shall respond that it was
                            most certainly not because I am unaware of my weakness; rather, I
                            recognize that in this kind<anchor type="annotation" n="90" xml:id="legacy90"/> of
                            intellectual battle, true profit lies in defeat. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028006" n="178"> It follows, then, that even--and
                            especially--the weak should not only take refuge in such battles, but
                            should literally seek them out. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028007" n="179"> He who has been defeated receives not an
                            injury, but an advantage, in that he returns home richer than when he
                            had set out: well educated and better equipped for future contests. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028008" n="180"> Though I am but a weak soldier, I am
                            nonetheless enlivened by this hope, and I have no fear of combat in so
                            difficult a battle against the strongest and most vigorous adversaries. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec028009" n="181"> As to whether this investigation is judged
                            reckless or otherwise, it is my hope that such decisions will be reached
                            with less regard to my age than to the ultimate outcome of the contest.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§29" xml:id="sec029">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec029001" n="182"> It remains in the third place for me to
                            answer those who take offence by the large number of my propositions, as
                            if this burden lay on their shoulders and it were not rather I alone who
                            have to endure this toil, as great as it may be. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec029002" n="183"> It is surely unbecoming and excessively
                            captious to wish to set limits to another's efforts and, as Cicero says,
                            to desire mediocrity in a matter where the greater is the better. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec029003" n="184"> In undertaking so great a venture it was
                            necessary for me either to fail or to succeed. If I should succeed, I do
                            not see why what is praiseworthy to do over ten theses should be deemed
                            blameworthy to do over nine hundred. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec029004" n="185"> If I should fail, they will have grounds for
                            accusing me, if they hate me and for excusing me, if they love me. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec029005" n="186"> For a young man who has failed through
                            weakness of talent or want of learning in so serious and great an
                            undertaking will be more deserving of pardon than of blame. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec029006" n="187"> Indeed, according to the poet: "If strength
                            fails, audacity will surely be praised; and in great undertaking to have
                            willed is enough." </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec029007" n="188"> And if many in our age, imitating Gorgias of
                            Leontini, have been accustomed, not without praise, to propose a
                            disputation not merely on nine hundred questions but on all questions
                            about all arts, why should I not be allowed to dispute without blame on
                            many questions indeed, but at least fixed and determined? </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§30" xml:id="sec030">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec030001" n="189"> But they say this is needless and ambitious. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030002" n="190"> Yet I contend that I did this not needlessly,
                            but of necessity; and if they should consider with me my reasons for
                            philosophizing, they must even reluctantly admit that it is clearly of
                            necessity. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030003" n="191"> For those who have devoted themselves to
                            anyone of the schools of philosophy, siding for instance with Thomas or
                            with Scotus, who are now most followed, can surely make trial of their
                            doctrines in the discussion of but a few questions. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030004" n="192"> But not to swear by anyone's word, I have
                            resolved myself to range through all masters of philosophy, to examine
                            all books, and to become acquainted with all schools. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030005" n="193"> Therefore, since I had to speak of all
                            philosophers, lest I might seem committed to a particular doctrine,
                            should I have, as its defender, neglected the others, there could not
                            fail to be very many questions concerning all of them together, even if
                            only a few about each one were severally proposed. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030006" n="194"> Nor should anyone condemn me for it, that
                            "wherever the circumstances bear me, there I am brought as a guest." </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030007" n="195"> For it was a rule observed by all the
                            ancients in studying every kind of writers never to pass over any
                            commentaries they were able to read, and especially by Aristotle, who
                            for this reason was called by Plato , that is, "the reader"; and it
                            certainly shows narrowness of mind to confine oneself within one Porch
                            or Academy. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030008" n="196"> Nor can anyone rightly choose his own
                            doctrine from all, unless he has first made himself familiar with all of
                            them. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec030009" n="197"> Moreover, there is in each school something
                            distinctive, which it has not in common with any other. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§31" xml:id="sec031">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec031001" n="198"> And now, to begin with the men of our own
                            faith to whom philosophy came last, we find in John [Duns] Scotus a
                            vigorous dialectic, in Thomas [Aquinas] a balanced solidity, in Giles
                            [of Rome] a neat precision, in Francis [of Meyronnes] a penetrating
                            acuteness, in Albert [the Great] an ancient and grand amplitude, in
                            Henry [of Ghent], as it has seemed to me, a constant and venerable
                            solemnity. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec031002" n="199"> Among the Arabs, we find in Averroes an
                            unshaken firmness, in Avempace, as in Al-Farabi a thoughtful
                            seriousness, in Avicenna a divine Platonic sublimity. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec031003" n="200"> Among the Greeks philosophy is certainly
                            terse in general and chaste in particular; in Simplicius it is rich and
                            copious, in Themistius elegant and compendious, in Alexander [of
                            Aphrodisias] learned and self-consistent, in Theophrastus seriously
                            worked out, in Ammonius smooth and agreeable. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec031004" n="201"> And if you turn to the Platonists, to mention
                            but a few, in Porphyry you will be pleased by the wealth of his topics
                            and the complexity of his religion; in Iamblichus you will be awed by an
                            occult philosophy and the mysteries of the barbarians; in Plotinus there
                            is no one thing in particular for you to admire, for he offers himself
                            to admiration in every part, as the Platonists themselves take pains
                            even in understanding his wisely allusive discourse, when he speaks
                            divinely of things divine and far aloof humanity of human things. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec031005" n="202"> I pass over the more recent ones, Proclus,
                            abunding in Asian fertility, and those who stem from him, Hermias,
                            Damascius, Olympiodorus, and many others, in all of whom that , that is,
                            that divine something which is the distinctive mark of the Platonists,
                            always shines out. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§32" xml:id="sec032">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec032001" n="203"> It should be added that, if there is a school
                            which attacks the more established truths and ridicules with calumny the
                            valid arguments of reason, it strengthens rather than weakens the truth
                            and, like a flame stirred by agitation, it excites rather than
                            extinguishes it. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032002" n="204"> This is the reason which has moved me in
                            wishing to call to the attention the opinions not only of a single
                            doctrine (as some would have liked), but of every sort of doctrine, so
                            that through the comparison of many schools and the discussion of
                            several philosophies that "effulgence of truth'' which Plato mentions in
                            his letters might shine more intensely to our minds, like a sun rising
                            from the high. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032003" n="205"> What would have been the point of dealing
                            only with the philosophy of the Latins, that is, of Albert, Thomas,
                            Scotus, Giles, Francis and Henry, leaving /137r/ the Greek and Arab
                            philosophers aside? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032004" n="206"> For all wisdom has flowed from the barbarians
                            to the Greeks and from the Greeks to us. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032005" n="207"> So our authors have always thought it enough
                            for them, in matters of philosophy, to rest on foreign discoveries and
                            to cultivate the doctrines of others. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032006" n="208"> What would have been the point of dealing
                            with natural things with the Peripatetics, without summoning the Academy
                            of the Platonists, whose doctrine on divine things, as Augustine
                            witnesses, has always been held the most sacred of all philosophies and
                            now, as far as I now, has been brought forward by me for the first time
                            after many centuries (may there be no envy in my words) to be submitted
                            to public disputation? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032007" n="209"> And what would have been the point of dealing
                            with the opinions of others, as many as they were, if like the one who
                            comes to the banquet of the wise without contributing anything, I should
                            bring nothing of mine, nothing produced and worked out by my own mind? </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032008" n="210"> It is certainly undignifying, as Seneca says,
                            to know only through the books and, as though the discoveries of our
                            ancestors had closed the way to our own industry and the power of nature
                            were exhausted in us, to bring about nothing from ourselves which, if it
                            could not demonstrate the truth, might at least hint to it even from
                            afar. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec032009" n="211"> For if a farmer hates sterility in his field
                            and a husband in his wife, certaily the divine mind the more will hate
                            the barren soul which is joined and associated with itself, the more it
                            expects from it a far nobler offspring. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§33" xml:id="sec033">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec033001" n="212"> Hence I have not been content to add, beside
                            the common doctrines, many principles taken from the ancient theology of
                            Hermes Trismegistus, many more drawn from the teachings of the Chaldeans
                            and of Pythagoras, and many others deriving from the more secret
                            mysteries of the Jews, and I have also proposed for disputation a good
                            many discoveries and reflections of my own both on things natural and
                            divine. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§34" xml:id="sec034">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec034001" n="213"> In the first place I have proposed the
                            concord of Plato and Aristotle, believed by many before me, but
                            adequately proved by no one. Among the Latins, Boethius promised to do
                            it, but there is no evidence that he has ever done what he always wished
                            to do. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec034002" n="214"> Among the Greeks, Simplicius made the same
                            declaration, but would that he had fulfilled his promise. 215. Agustine
                            too writes that there were not a few Achademics who tried with their
                            most subtle arguments to prove the same thing, namely, that the
                            philosophy of Plato and Aristotle was the same. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec034003" n="216"> John [Philoponos] the Grammarian likewise,
                            although he says that Plato differs from Aristotle only for those who do
                            not understand what Plato says, nevertheless left it to posterity to
                            prove it. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec034004" n="217"> I have also added many theses where I
                            maintain that several statements by Thomas and Scotus which are thought
                            to be discordant are in agreement, and many others where I maintain the
                            same about statements by Averroes and Avicenna. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§35" xml:id="sec035">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec035001" n="218"> In the second place, whoever holds not only
                            the theses which I have discovered both in the Aritotelian and in the
                            Platonic philosophy, but also the seventy-two new theses which I have
                            proposed both in physics and in metaphysics (if I am not wrong, as will
                            soon be clear to me) will be able to solve any question proposed about
                            things natural and divine on a principle quite other than we are taught
                            by that philosophy which is read in the schools and cultivated by the
                            doctors of this age. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec035002" n="219"> Nor it ought to induce so much to amazement
                            that in my early years, at a tender age at which, as some contend, one
                            is hardly permitted to read the works of others, I should wish to
                            introduce a new philosophy, as much as it ought to induce either to
                            praise if it is defensible, or to condemnation, if it is refutable,
                            those who in the end, when they will judge of my discoveries and my
                            learning, should reckon up not the years of their author, but rather
                            their own merits or demerits. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§36" xml:id="sec036">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec036001" n="220"> There is, beside this, still another way of
                            philosophizing by means of numbers, which I have presented as new, but
                            which is in fact old, and was observed by the ancient theologians, by
                            Pythagoras in particular, by Aglaophamos, Philolaus and Plato, and by
                            the earlier Platonists. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036002" n="221"> But in this age, this doctrine, like other
                            famous ones, has so passed out of use by the carelessness of posterity,
                            that hardly any traces of it are to be found. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036003" n="222"> Plato writes in the Epinomis that, among all
                            liberal arts and contemplative sciences the science of number /137v/ is
                            the chief and most divine. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036004" n="223"> And again, asking why man is the wisest of
                            animals, he answers, "Because he knows how to number". </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036005" n="224"> Aristotle also mentions this opinion in his
                            Problems. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036006" n="225"> Abumasar writes that it was a saying of
                            Avenzoar of Babylon that he who knows how to number knows all things. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036007" n="226"> These things could not possibly be true if
                            they had understood by the art of number that art at which now the
                            merchants are especially skilful. Also Plato witnesses this, when he
                            openly warns us not to believe that this divine arithmetic be the
                            arithmetic of the merchants. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec036008" n="227"> Since it seemed to me, after long nights of
                            study, that I had thoroughly examined that arithmetic which is so
                            praised, in order to put these matters to a test, I promised that I
                            would answer in public through the art of number to seventy-four
                            questions which are considered among the most important in physics and
                            divinity. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§37" xml:id="sec037">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec037001" n="228"> I have also proposed some theses about magic,
                            in which I have shown that there are two forms of magic, one of which
                            depends entirely on the work and powers of demons and is, in my faith,
                            an execrable and monstrous thing. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037002" n="229"> The other is, when keenly examined, nothing
                            but the absolute perfection of natural philosophy. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037003" n="230"> The Greeks mentioned both of them, but they
                            call the former * * * , by no means honouring it by the name of magic,
                            wheres they call the latter by the proper and exclusive name of * * * ,
                            the perfect and highest wisdom, as it were. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037004" n="231"> As a matter fact, as Porphyry says, in the
                            Persian language magus means the same as expert and interpreter of
                            divine things with us. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037005" n="232"> So there is a great or even, Fathers, the
                            greatest difference and disparity between these two arts. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037006" n="233"> The former is condemned and abhorred not only
                            by the Christian religion, but by all laws and every well-constituted
                            state. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037007" n="234"> The latter is approved and embraced by all
                            wise men and all peoples devoted to heavenly and divine things. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037008" n="235"> The former is the most deceitful of arts, the
                            latter is the highest and most holy philosophy. The former is sterile
                            and vain, the latter is sure, reliable and firm. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037009" n="236"> The former has always been concealed by
                            whoever has practised it, because it would have been shameful and
                            ignominious to its author, whereas since antiquity the highest renown
                            and glory of letters has almost always been expected from the latter. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037010" n="237"> No philosopher nor man eager to learn good
                            arts has ever been studious the former, but to learn the latter
                            Pythagoras, Empedocles, Plato and Democritus crossed the seas, taught it
                            when they returned and held it chief among the arcane doctrines. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037011" n="238"> The former is not based on any principles nor
                            approved by any reliable author; the latter, ennobled as it were by most
                            celebrated parents, has two authors above all: Zalmolxis, who was
                            imitated by Abbaris the Hyperborean, and Zoroaster, not the one of whom
                            perhaps you are thinking, but the son of Oromasius. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037012" n="239"> If we ask Plato what is the magic of both
                            these men, he will answer in the Alcibiades that the magic of Zoroaster
                            is nothing else than that science of divine things in which the kings of
                            the Persians educated their sons, so that they might learn to rule their
                            state on the example of the order of the universe. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec037013" n="240"> And in the Charmides he will answer that the
                            magic of Zamolxis is the medicine of the soul, or that medicine by which
                            temperance is obtained for the soul, as by the other one health is
                            obtained for the body. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="§38" xml:id="sec038">
                    <p/>
                    <div type="body">
                        <p xml:id="sec038001" n="241"> Afterwards Charondas, Damigeron, Apollonius,
                            Osthanes and Dardanus persevered in their footsteps. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038002" n="242"> And so did Homer, who concealed this wisdom
                            too, in the manner he concealed all the other ones, under the wanderings
                            of his Ulysses, as I shall sometime prove in my Poetic Theology. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038003" n="243"> Eudoxus and Hermippus persevered. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038004" n="244"> And almost all who have examined closely the
                            Pythagorean and Platonic mysteries have persevered. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038005" n="245"> Among the later philosophers, then, I find
                            three who have scented it, the Arabian Al-Kindi, Roger Bacon and William
                            of Paris. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038006" n="246"> Plotinus also mentions it, where he shows
                            that a magus is the minister and not the maker of nature. That most wise
                            man approves /138r/ and justifies this kind of magic, so abhorring the
                            other that, invited to the rites of evil demons, he said that it was
                            more fitting for them to come to him than for him to go to them, and
                            rightly so. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038007" n="247"> For just as the former makes man a slave and
                            pawn of wicked powers, the latter makes him their lord and master. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038008" n="248"> The former, in the end, cannot claim for
                            itself the name of euther art or science, whereas the latter, full as it
                            is of the loftiest mysteries, comprises the deepest contemplation of the
                            most secret things and ultimately the knowledge of all nature. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038009" n="249"> The latter, in calling out, as it were, from
                            their hiding places into the light the good powers scattered and sown in
                            the world by the benevolent care of God, does not so much make miracles,
                            as sedulously serve nature which makes them. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038010" n="250"> Having looked with deeper insight into that
                            harmony of the universe, which the Greeks more expressively call , and
                            having observed the mutual cognition that natures have of each other,
                            this latter, by addressing to each thing its innate charms, which are
                            called called the of the magicians, brings out into the open, as if it
                            were itself the maker, the miracles lying hidden in the recesses of the
                            world, in the womb of nature, in the mysterious storerooms of God, and,
                            as the farmer marries elm to vine, so does the magus marry earth to
                            heaven, that is, the lower things to the endowments and powers of the
                            higher. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038011" n="251"> Hence it comes about that the former appears
                            as monstrous and harmful, as the latter divine and salutary. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038012" n="252"> And chiefly because the former, in subjecting
                            man to the enemies of God, drives him away from Him, whereas the latter
                            prompts him to admire the works of God, so that most surely follow such
                            charity, faith and hope that lean on Him. </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038013" n="253"> For nothing induces us more to religion and
                            the worship of God than the assiduous contemplation of His wonders, so
                            that, should we have aptly examined them by means of this natural magic
                            I am discussing, more ardently aroused to the worship and love of their
                            maker, we would be forced to sing: "The heavens are full, all of the
                            earth is full of the majesty of Thy glory." </p>
                        <p xml:id="sec038014" n="254"> But this is enough about magic and I have
                            said this much about it because I know that there are many who, just as
                            dogs always bark at strangers, so they hate too what they do not
                            understand. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
